Theodore R. Cogswell Papers
Theodore R. Cogswell Papers
1935-1988
Cogswell, Theodore R.
9.5 linear ft.
Papers of the American author, science fiction writer, professor. Includes correspondence and writings, including plays, poems, and short stories.
149403
Biographical History
Theodore R. Cogswell (1918-1987) was an American science fiction author. In 1937 he joined the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (formally known as the XV International Brigade) and served as an ambulance driver during the Spanish Civil war. During World War II he served with the U.S. Army Air Corps in Asia.
His first published story was "The Specter General" in Astounding in 1952. Most of his stories were light-hearted humorous pieces; he also co-authored (with Charles A. Spano) the Star Trek novel Spock, Messiah!.
Cogswell had a master's degree in English and taught at Keystone Junior College in Pennsylvania and at Ball State University in Muncie, Indiana. In 1959 he launched the long-running (1962-1979) fanzine Proceedings of the Institute for Twenty-First Century Studies, in which writers and editors discussed their own and each other's works, and he was for several years secretary for the Science Fiction Writers of America and editor of its Forum.
Cogswell was married three times: to Marjorie Mills (1948), to Coralie Norris (1964), and to George (or Georgia) Rae Marsh (1972). He had two daughters, Megan and Cathe.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Theodore R. Cogswell Papers contains correspondence, memorabilia, printed material, and writings.
Correspondence consists of both incoming and outgoing correspondence with publishers, agents, fellow authors, friends and family. Notable correspondents represented in the collection include Poul Anderson, Isaac Asimov, Alfred Bester, James Blish, Ben Bova, Ray Bradbury, John W. Campbell, Suzy McKee Charnas, Arthur C. Clarke, Avram Davidson, Gordon R. Dickson, G. C. Edmondson, Philip Jose Farmer, James Gunn, Harry Harrison, Robert Heinlein, Damon Knight, Jay Klein ("Jay Kay"), Ursula Le Guin, Anne McCaffrey, Vonda McIntyre, Andrew Offutt, Alexei Panshin, Frederik Pohl, Gene Roddenberry, Joanna Russ, Pamela Sargent, James Tiptree, Kurt Vonnegut, Kate Wilhelm, and Chelsea Quinn Yarbro, among others. A large segment of correspondence relates to offices Cogswell held in the Science Fiction Writers of America, including discussions of dues, membership requirements, the SFWA publication Forum, and resolution of intra-society disagreements. There is also material from Cogswell's Institute for Twenty First Century Studies (ITCFS), including several issues of its Proceedings. Unrelated to science fiction, but of historical interest, is Cogswell's correspondence with fellow veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, more properly known as the XV International Brigade, with whom he served in the 1930s (e.g. Ben Iceland, Irving Weissman).
Memorabilia includes items related to Cogswell's military service in both the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in the 1930s and the United States Army Air Corps during World War II. There are also clippings about him and by him, and several facetious Who's Who application forms.
Printed material contains a number of fanzines, at least one of which (Citadel) contains a piece by Cogswell, as well as issues of various publications containing stories by Cogswell. There is also some military miscellany and a small booklet published by Hugo Gernsback.
Writings encompasses articles, book reviews, essays, plays/scripts, poems, songs and stories. Several of the songs include both lyrics and music. The material is a mix of handwritten drafts and notes, typed drafts, typed final copy, typescript carbons and (very occasionally) a few bits of correspondence pertaining to the item. Essays include a piece on Soviet bloc science fiction. Plays/scripts include a number of murder mysteries ("The W. S. Murder Case" and "Rocky King, Detective: Murder on the Midway"). Stories encompasses short stories, novellas and novels, including extensive material -- handwritten drafts, typed drafts, etc. -- relating to Spock, Messiah, one of the first Star Trek novels, which Cogswell co-wrote with Charles Spano.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is arranged alphabetically by name, subject, or title. Within each individual correspondent folder, correspondence is arranged chronologically.
Related Material
has the papers of a number of science fiction and fantasy authors as well as an extensive collection of early science fiction and fantasy magazines and 'zines and a large book collection. Please refer to for a complete listing of manuscript collections; for more information on the magazines, 'zines, and books please contact the repository listed above.
Subject and Genre Headings
Science fiction; Literature -- American Fiction; Anderson, Poul, 1926-2001.; Asimov, Isaac, 1920-1992.; Charnas, Suzy McKee.; Clarke, Arthur C. (Arthur Charles), 1917-2008.; Cogswell, Theodore R.; Davidson, Avram.; Derleth, August, 1909-1971.; Edmondson, G. C.; Ellison, Harlan.; Farmer, Philip José.; Gunn, James E., 1923-; Harrison, Harry, 1925-2012.; Heinlein, Robert A. (Robert Anson), 1907-1988.; Kidd, Virginia.; Knight, Damon, 1922-2002.; Le Guin, Ursula K., 1929-; McCaffrey, Anne.; McIntyre, Vonda N.; Offutt, Andrew J.; Pohl, Frederik.; Pournelle, Jerry, 1933-; Reynolds, Mack.; Russ, Joanna, 1937-2011.; Sargent, Pamela.; Seeger, Pete, 1919-2014.; Simak, Clifford D., 1904-1988.; Tiptree, James, Jr., 1915-1987.; Vonnegut, Kurt.; Yarbro, Chelsea Quinn, 1942-; Abraham Lincoln Brigade.; Institute for Twenty-first Century Studies.; Kerista Commune.; Science Fiction Writers of America.; Spock, messiah.; American literature -- 20th century.; Authors, American.; Science fiction, American.; Science fiction plays, American.; Science fiction poetry, American.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- Burma.; Sound recordings.; Book reviews.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Drafts (documents); Fanzines.; Manuscripts for publication.; Memorabilia.; Photographs.; Poems.; Scripts (documents); Authors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Theodore Cogswell, 1971.
Gift of George Rae (Mrs. Theodore) Cogswell, 1987.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Adams, Robert, 1977; undated (Box 1)
  - Aldiss, Brian, 1971; 1974 (Box 1)
  - Allyn & Bacon, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Altshuler, Harry, 1954-1961 (Box 1)
  - Amis, Kingsley, 1961; 1963 (Box 1)
  - Anderson, Poul, 1954; 1956,; 1965-1970,; 1980,; 1983-1988 (Box 1)
  - Anthony, Piers, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - Arnason, Eleanor (Box 1)
  - Asimov, Isaac, 1955; 1960,; 1963,; 1970-1974,; 1980 (Box 1)
  - ATLAS (Alfred Balk), 1975 (Box 1)
  - A, misc (Box 1)
  - Ball State University, 1957-1958; 1963-1964,; 1976 (Box 1)
  - Ballantine (Judy-Lyn Del Rey), 1970-1971; 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - Bantam Books, 1975-1976; 1978,; 1984 (Box 1)
  - Bear, Greg, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Belin Arts Scholarship Committee, 1971; includes letters of recommendation from numerous authors including Isaac Asimov, Alfred Bester and August Derleth (Box 1)
  - Benford, Gregory, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Berman, Ruth (Box 1)
    See also Arnason, Eleanor.
  - Bernstein, Philip, 1981-1984 (Box 1)
  - Bessie, Alvah, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Bester, Alfred, 1970-1972; 1974,; undated (Box 1)
  - Biggle, Lloyd, 1970-1976 (Box 1)
  - Bischoff, Dave, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Bishop, Michael, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Blish, James, 1970-1971; 1974,; 1978 (Box 1)
  - Bloch, Robert, 1975; 1986 (Box 1)
  - Boucher, Tony, See Fantasy & Science Fiction.
  - Bova, Ben, 1970-1978; 1984 (Box 1)
  - Bradbury, Ray, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Bradley, Marion Zimmer, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Bretnor, Reg, 1973; 1978-1980,; undated (Box 1)
  - Broxon, Mildred Downey, 1974-1977; 1980-1981 (Box 1)
  - Brunner, John, 1966; 1975,; 1980 (Box 1)
  - Buckley, William F., undated; outgoing only (Box 1)
  - Budrys, Algis, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Busby, F. M., 1974-1977; 1980 (Box 1)
  - B, misc (Box 1)
  - John W. Campbell, 1951; 1961,; 1971,; 1976,; undated (Box 1)
  - Carpenter, John, undated (Box 1)
  - Carter, Lin, undated (Box 1)
  - Center for the Study of Popular Culture, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Center for the Study of Science Fiction (University of Kansas), See Gunn, James.
  - Chandler, A. Bertram, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - Charnas, Suzy McKee, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - Charnock, Graham, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Ciardi, John, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Clareson, Tom, 1960; 1972,; 1974,; 1977 (Box 2)
  - Clarke, Arthur C., 1963; 1970-1971,; 1974-1975,; undated (Box 2)
    See also Russ, Joanna.
  - Cogswell, Cathe and Terry Moran (daughter, son-in-law), 1977; 1980,; undated (Box 2)
  - Cogswell, Coralie (wife), 1974; 1984,; undated (Box 2)
  - Cogswell, DeWitt R. and Margarett (parents), 1937-1940; 1944,; 1965,; 1982 (Box 2)
  - Cogswell, George Rae (wife), 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - Cogswell, Megan (daughter), 1970-1971; 1974,; 1979,; 1984[?] (Box 2)
  - ConFusion, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Conklin, Groff, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Cook, Glen, undated (Box 2)
  - Coulson, Robert "Buck", 1970-1975 (Box 2)
  - C, misc (Box 2)
  - Dann, Jack, 1972; undated (Box 2)
  - Davenport, Basil, 1958; 1960,; 1963,; 1970,; undated; includes review of Cogswell's "Neutral corner"; letter from Davenport's son (Box 2)
  - Davidson, Avram, 1963-1966; 1970-1971,; 1973,; 1981,; 1986,; undated (Box 2)
  - Davidson, Joel and Sherri, 1975-1984 (Box 2)
  - De Camp, L. Sprague, 1960; 1970-1976 (Box 2)
  - De Ford, Miriam Allen, 1964; 1971-1972,; 1974-1975 (Box 2)
  - DeLap, Richard, 1970; 1976 (Box 2)
  - Derleth, August, 1960 (Box 2)
  - DeVine, James, 1972; 1975-1977 (Box 2)
  - Dick, Philip K., 1975; undated (Box 2)
  - Dickson, Gordon R. ("Gordy"), 1957; 1965,; 1971,; undated (Box 2)
  - Disch, Tom, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Dozois, Gardner, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Drake, David, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Duvic, Patrice, 1976; undated (Box 2)
  - D, misc (Box 2)
  - Edelstein, Scott, 1973; undated (Box 2)
  - Edmondson, G. C. ("GCE"), 1960; 1970,; 1972-1973,; 1979-1978 (Box 2)
  - Eisenstein, Phyllis, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Ellison, Harlan, 1971; 1973-1974,; 1976,; 1984 (Box 2)
    See also Rogue (magazine).
  - Elwood, Roger, 1973-1974 (Box 2)
  - Emshwiller, Ed, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Etchison, Dennis, 1973 (Box 2)
    See also "Dennis" in Unidentified - First name only file; likely the same person.
  - Extrapolation, See Clareson, Tom.
  - E, misc (Box 2)
  - Feinstein, Becky and Simon, 1964; 1975 (Box 2)
  - Fantasy & Science Fiction, 1953-1958; 1962,; 1970,; 1975 (Box 2)
  - Farmer, Philip Jose, 1970-1971; 1975,; 1977,; 1979,; undated (Box 2)
  - First Fandom, 1973-1974; 1981,; 1984 (Box 2)
  - FitzPatrick, Al, 1975; 1978,; 1983,; 1986,; undated (Box 2)
  - Foster, Alan Dean, 1971; 1977 (Box 2)
  - Fuentes, Roberto, 1974-1975 (Box 3)
  - Funnell, Augustine ("Gus"), 1986 (Box 3)
  - F, misc (Box 3)
  - Geis, Richard, 1976; undated (Box 3)
  - Gerrold, David, 1971; 1975,; undated (Box 3)
  - G. K. Hall & Co., 1979-1981; undated; regarding Gregg Press publishing proceedings of the ITFCS (Box 3)
  - Glauber, Gary, 1983-1984 (Box 3)
  - Gold, Horace L., 1956-1957; undated (Box 3)
  - Goldin, Steve, 1971; 1974-1976 (Box 3)
  - Goldsmith, Howard, 1974-1977 (Box 3)
  - Graham, Roger Phillips, See Phillips, Rog.
  - Grant, C. L. ("Charlie"), 1971-1977 (Box 3)
  - Green, Joe, 1973-1975; 1981 (Box 3)
  - Green, Roland J., 1974 (Box 3)
  - Greenberg, Martin H., 1974 (Box 3)
  - Gunn, James, 1970-1971; 1975-1976,; 1983,; undated (Box 3)
  - G, misc (Box 3)
  - Haldeman, Joe, 1970; 1977,; 1979,; 1981 (Box 3)
  - Hamilton, Dorothy, undated (Box 3)
  - Harper's Weekly, 1975-1976 (Box 3)
  - Harrison, Harry, 1961-1980; 1986,; undated (Box 3)
  - Heinlein, Robert and Ginny, 1959; 1962,; 1976-1977,; 1984 (Box 3)
  - Hensley, Joe, 1960; 1970-1971 (Box 3)
  - Herb Jaffe Assoc., 1959-1960; undated (Box 3)
  - Herrick, William ("Bill"), 1971 (Box 3)
  - Hodgens, Richard M., 1970-1971 (Box 3)
  - Hollis, H. H., 1971-1972 (Box 3)
  - Holly, J. Hunter (Joan Carol), 1974; 1976 (Box 3)
  - H, misc (Box 3)
  - Iceland, Ben, 1981-1986; VALB (Box 3)
  - Institute for Twenty First Century Studies (ITFCS)
    - Correspondence, 1960; 1965-1976 (Box 3)
    - Digit vol 1 no 1 (Box 3)
    - Proceedings #127-136 (Box 3)
    - Proceedings #137-139 (Oversize 1)
    - Proceedings #140-143 (Box 3)
    - Proceedings #148-149 (Box 4)
    - Miscellany, includes membership application, sketches of logos, listings for Ulrich's and other periodicals directories (Box 4)
  - Isaac Asimov's Science Fiction Magazine, 1976; 1983 (Box 4)
  - Isaacs, Linda (Linan), 1974-1975 (Box 4)
  - I, misc (Box 4)
  - Jakes, John, 1970 (Box 4)
  - J, misc (Box 4)
  - Kaye, Marvin, 1984 (Box 4)
  - Keystone Junior College, 1969-1972; 1978,; 1982-1983 (Box 4)
  - Kidd, Virginia, 1970-1980; James Blish's ex-wife; Cogswell's literary agent (Box 4)
  - King, Diana, 1972-1973; 1978,; undated (Box 4)
  - Klein, Jay K. (Jay Kay), 1970-1983 (Box 4)
  - Knight, Damon, 1960; 1970-1975,; 1980,; undated (Box 4)
  - K, misc (Box 4)
  - Labakow, Louis, See First Fandom.
  - Landis, Art, 1978-1980; 1984,; 1986 (Box 4)
  - Laumer, Keith, 1971 (Box 4)
  - Le Guin, Ursula K., 1971; 1975-1976 (Box 4)
  - Leiber, Fritz, 1967; 1974 (Box 4)
  - Lem, Stanislaw, 1975; outgoing only (Box 4)
  - Levant, Howard, 1978 (Box 4)
  - Ley, Willy, 1960 (Box 4)
  - Lichtenberg, Jacqueline, 1975-1977 (Box 4)
  - Lowndes, Robert A. W. ("RAW"), 1970 (Box 4)
  - L, misc (Box 4)
  - MacDonald, Wayne, undated (Box 4)
  - Malamud, Bernard, 1971 (Box 4)
  - Malzberg, Barry, 1970-1971; 1974-1975,; 1978 (Box 4)
  - Margroff, Robert E., 1971; 1974 (Box 4)
  - Martin, Fredericka ("Freddie"), 1978-1980 (Box 4)
  - Martin, George R. R., 1974-1976 (Box 4)
  - McAllister, Bruce, 1974 (Box 4)
  - McCaffrey, Anne, 1960; 1976 (Box 4)
  - McCauley, Kirby, 1975-1977; 1980; literary agent; includes client list, photocopy of letter from L. Ron Hubbard to Forrest Ackerman (Box 4)
  - McEvoy, Seth, 1974-1975 (Box 4)
  - McIntyre, Vonda, 1970-1977 (Box 4)
  - Memmler, Hal, 1974; 1976 (Box 4)
  - Mensa, 1971-1972; 1974 (Box 4)
  - Meredith, Scott, 1951-1957; 1970,; 1974,; undated; Cogswell's literary agent; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Merrill, Judith, 1959; 1965-1969,; 1979; includes two royalty summaries (Box 5)
  - Milford Science Fiction Writers Conference, 1956; 1961,; 1968 (Box 5)
  - Miller, Walter M. Jr., 1960 (Box 5)
  - Mills, Robert P., 1957; 1960-1973,; undated (Box 5)
  - Morressy, John, 1974 (Box 5)
  - M, misc (Box 5)
  - NASA, 1975-1977 (Box 5)
  - Nelson, Ray (R. Faraday), 1977 (Box 5)
  - Neville, Kris, 1972; 1974-1975,; undated (Box 5)
  - Niven, Larry, 1974 (Box 5)
  - Norden, Hans, 1971-1975 (Box 5)
  - Norton, Andre, 1962 (Box 5)
  - Norville, Barbara, undated (Box 5)
  - Nourse, Alan E., 1960; 1971,; undated (Box 5)
  - N, misc (Box 5)
  - Offutt, Andrew and Jodie, 1971-1976 (Box 5)
  - Overstreet, Lee, 1974-1976 (Box 5)
  - O, misc (Box 5)
  - Pangborn, Edgar, 1970 (Box 5)
  - Panshin, Alexei, 1964 (Box 5)
  - Payes, Rachel (Mrs. Norman), 1970-1971; 1974-1976,; 1984; includes article, "Badverbs" (Box 5)
  - Pflock, Karl T., 1974-1975; 1977 (Box 5)
  - Phillips, Rog, 1960 (Box 5)
  - Pierce, John R., 1960; 1970 (Box 5)
  - Pierson, Louis Randall (Box 5)
  - Pohl, Frederik, 1960; 1974-1977,; undated (Box 5)
  - Porter, Andrew, 1974 (Box 5)
  - Pournelle, Jerry, 1971-1977; undated (Box 5)
  - Prago, Albert, 1984-1986; undated (Box 5)
  - Presmont, Jud and Joy, 1967; regarding Kerista commune (Box 5)
  - Priest, Christopher, 1971 (Box 5)
  - Prizel, Yuri, 1973-1975; undated (Box 5)
  - Pronzini, Bill, 1970 (Box 5)
  - Pumilia, Joseph, 1971 (Box 5)
  - Purdom, Tom, 1970-1976 (Box 5)
  - Pyramid Publications, 1962; 1969,; 1974 (Box 5)
  - P, misc (Box 5)
  - Q, misc (Box 5)
  - Reynolds, Mack, 1957; 1966,; 1971-1980 (Box 5)
  - Roddenberry, Gene, 1976-1977 (Box 5)
  - Rogue (magazine), 1959-1960; editors Harlan Ellison, Frank Robinson (Box 5)
  - Ross, Adolph, 1983-1984; VALB (Box 5)
  - Runton, Charles W., 1974-1975 (Box 5)
  - Ruse, Gary Alan, 1974-1977 (Box 5)
  - Rusher, William A., 1983-1986; National Review (Box 5)
  - Russ, Joanna, 1974-1975; includes two letters to Arthur C. Clarke (Box 5)
  - R, misc (Box 5)
  - Santesson, Hans Stefan, 1960; 1971 (Box 6)
  - Sargent, Pamela, 1970-1977; undated (Box 6)
  - Science Fiction Writers of America (SFWA)
    - Correspondence, 1965; 1969-1974; bulk is to or from Tom Purdom, Andy Offutt, Jerry Pournelle, Vonda McIntyre, Chelsea Quinn Yarbro, but almost all authors in the inventory are also represented in these folders; 6 folders (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, 1975-1979; undated; bulk is to or from Tom Purdom, Andy Offutt, Jerry Pournelle, Vonda McIntyre, Chelsea Quinn Yarbro, but almost all authors in the inventory are also represented in these folders; 5 folders (Box 7)
    - Printed material, 1970; undated; includes SFWA brochures, one issue of Forum, info on Science Fiction Writers Speakers Bureau, etc. (Box 7)
  - Scientology, 1970-1971 (Box 7)
  - Scithers, George (Owlswick Press), 1970-1974; 1976,; 1984 (Box 7)
  - Scott Meredith Literary Agency, See Meredith, Scott.
  - Scranton Times (Dan Cusick), 1978 (Box 7)
  - Seeger, Pete, 1961; regarding some of Cogswell's songs (Box 7)
  - SFExpo 76, 1975-1976 (Box 7)
  - Shibano, Takumi, 1986 (Box 7)
  - Shultz, Dyson P., 1971-1972 (Box 7)
  - Silverber, Robert, 1970 (Box 7)
  - Simak, Clifford, 1960; 1970-1971,; 1977; cogswell_001; includes audiorecording of Simak "On the short story" (Box 7)
  - Sirois, Al, 1974 (Box 7)
  - Smith, Evelyn E., 1960; 1964,; undated (Box 7)
  - Smith, George O. (GOSmith), undated (Box 7)
  - Society of Mayflower Descendants, 1972-1973 (Box 7)
  - Sorensen, Bob (Minneapolis Tribune), 1971-1972 (Box 7)
  - Spinrad, Norman, undated (Box 7)
  - Star Trek Convention, 1975 (Box 7)
  - Stephenson, Andrew, 1974-1976 (Box 7)
  - Stock, Stuart H., 1978-1979; 1981; regarding ParaCon (Box 7)
  - Strete, Craig, 1974; undated (Box 7)
  - Sturgeon, Theodore, undated (Box 7)
  - Swain, Dwight V., 1974-1976; 1978 (Box 7)
  - S, misc (Box 7)
  - Tall, Stephen, 1971 (Box 8)
  - Thomas, Theodore (Ted), 1964; 1971-1977,; 1984,; 1986 (Box 8)
  - Tiptree, James, 1973-1976 (Box 8)
  - Tofte, Arthur, 1974 (Box 8)
  - Trestrail, Verna, 1965; daughter of E. E. "Doc" Smith; includes copy of Smith's obituary (Box 8)
  - Tuning, William, 1974-1977; including issue of Santa Barbara Life, of which Tuning was managing editor (Box 8)
  - T, misc (Box 8)
  - United Nations, 1970 (Box 8)
  - United States intelligence agencies, various, 1940s; 1975; includes FBI, CIA, U.S. Army, etc., relating to files on Cogswell arising from his service in the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, which was suspected of ties to the Communist Party; much of the contents is photocopies of file material from the 1940s; 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Universal Life Church, 1970 (Box 8)
  - University of Denver, 1955; 1958,; 1965,; 1968-1969,; 1971 (Box 8)
  - Utley, Steven, 1974 (Box 8)
  - U, misc (Box 8)
  - Van Scyoc, Sydney, 1974 (Box 8)
  - Van Vogt, A. E., 1970; 1975,; undated (Box 8)
  - Vardeman, Robert E., 1974; 1977 (Box 8)
  - Versins, Pierre, 1961 (Box 8)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB), 1975-1976; 1979,; 1983-1984,; 1986; see also (Box 8)
    See also Iceland, Ben; Weissman, Irving; Memorabilia: Abraham Lincoln Brigade.
  - Vonnegut, Kurt, 1960; 1971,; 1974,; 1985; includes two from "Kilgore Trout" (Box 8)
  - V, misc (Box 8)
  - Wandrei, Donald, 1973; 1976 (Box 9)
  - Warren, George, 1976-1977 (Box 9)
  - Wayman, Tony Russell, 1970 (Box 9)
  - Wayne, Taral, See MacDonald, Wayne.
  - Weissman, Irving, 1986; undated; VALB (Box 9)
  - Wilhelm, Kate, 1970; 1974 (Box 9)
  - Williamson, Jack, 1975; 1979,; 1983 (Box 9)
  - Wilson, Gahan, 1976 (Box 9)
  - Wodhams, Jack, 1970; 1984; includes lengthy letter on the defects of the word processor, with original cartoon illustrations (Box 9)
  - Wolle, Francis, 1970 (Box 9)
  - World Science Fiction Convention, 1973; 1975 (Box 9)
  - Writers Institute, 1975-1976 (Box 9)
  - Wyal, Pg, 1974-1976 (Box 9)
  - W, misc (Box 9)
  - Yarbro, Chelsea Quinn, See Science Fiction Writers of America (SFWA).
  - Y, misc (Box 9)
  - Zebrowski, George, 1970 (Box 9)
  - Unidentified, first name A-Z, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Unidentified, no name or illegible (Box 9)
- Memorabilia
  - 3d Combat Cargo Group, North Burma Campaign summary (Box 9)
  - Abraham Lincoln Brigade, "Roster of 790th Quartermaster Truck Company, Davis-Monthan Field, Tucson, Arizona"; group photo (Box 9)
  - Birth certificate (Box 9)
  - Clippings about Cogswell, 1938; 1971,; 1976-1977,; undated; includes review of Spock, Messiah (Box 9)
  - Clippings by Cogswell, 1970; 1975,; 1979,; undated (Box 9)
  - Curriculum vitae, circa 1977 (Box 9)
  - Maps (Box 9)
  - Military miscellany, 1935; 1937,; undated (Box 9)
  - Publications list (Box 9)
  - Wedding to George, 1972 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous, includes humorous "Who's Who" applications (Box 9)
- Printed material
  - 1966 Forecast (Gernsback), booklet, 32pp (Box 9)
  - Climax, 1953; contains story "Time telescoped" by Cogswell, also a photocopy of those pages (Box 9)
  - Convention Annual #1: PittCon, 1960 (Box 9)
  - DISCON: Proceedings, 1963 (Box 9)
  - Fanzines
    - Bibliographica Futurica Fantastica, 1967; vol. 1 no. 3 (Box 10)
    - Citadel (George and Lana Proctor), "How Dinosaurs Did It" issue (Box 10)
      See also Writings: Articles: How did the dinosaurs do it?.
    - Differential (Paul Wyszkowski), 1964-1965; #20, 32, 33 (Box 10)
    - Fancom (Paul Wyszkowski), No. 4, 5 (Box 10)
    - MFS Bulletin (Rich Elsberry, Dale Rostomily), 1951; No. 35; includes "Last Journey of Sad Sam" by Cogswell (Box 10)
    - Odd Magazine, 1968; #18 (Box 10)
    - The Vinegar Worm (Bob Leman) (Box 10)
    - Voice of the Turtle (Joyce and Raymond Fisher), 1967; #16 (Box 10)
    - [unidentified] (Ruth Berman), 1970; #6 (Box 10)
  - Harper's Weekly, 1975; article by Cogswell, "You can fool most of the people most of the time" about his PITFCS (Box 10)
  - Manifesto [of the] Suspended College Students Federation for the Liberated Areas of China, circa 1944 (Box 10)
  - Military miscellany, 1945; undated; includes clippings from TIME with photographs of concentration camp victims, with handwritten note in margin "I must not forget this" (Box 10)
  - Venture, Jul 1957; story "Aces Loaded" by Cogswell (Box 10)
  - The Window, May 1948; pp 3 and 4, containing poems by Cogswell (Box 10)
- Writings
  - Articles
    - The Compleat impostor (publisher in Harper's Weekly as "You can fool most of the people most of the time")
    - Dante, Chaucer and Spenser article (Box 10)
    - Fire, ice, or a five-dollar subway fare (Box 10)
    - Hints as to the nature of the loved one (Box 10)
    - How did the dinosaurs do it? (Box 10)
      See also Printed material: Citadel.
    - Kirlian photographym diagnostic tool?, includes correspondence with Nova, notes (Box 10)
    - On critical acclaim (Box 10)
    - The population implosion, includes photocopy of published version (Box 10)
    - Vitamin E and documentation, 1971; multiple drafts, published article, extensive notes and clippings on the subject (Box 10)
    - Some like them hot (Box 10)
  - Book reviews
    - Dickson, Gordon R. / Sleepwalker's World, 1971; typescript, clipping of published version (Box 10)
    - Magruder, Richard / Snob's Guide to Acapulco, 1971; clipping of published version only (Box 10)
    - Russ, Joanna / And Chaos Died, 1971; typescript, clipping of published version (Box 10)
    - Simak, Clifford / A Choice of Gods, Destiny Doll, Out of Their Minds, 1971-1972; typescript, clipping of published version (Box 10)